Right. Well, good morning and welcome.
We have Laura McClure before us this morning on the Deepfake,
Digital Harm and Exploitation Bill. And welcome, Laura.
We have 15 minutes with you this morning.
You want to take us, the committee, through your bill, and
if you wish to leave some time for questions.
Great. Well, thank you, Mr Chair, and thank you to the committee for having me
today. Firstly, I just want to say thank you to all of those that have
submitted on this bill. A lot of very detailed
submissions, which is great. I think it's been well traversed
in the House as to why I brought this legislation forward.
It's absolutely disgusting and abhorrent that someone can be
deepfaked into
pornography or sexually explicit material without their consent, and we know
that this is increasing year on year.
96% of victims are female,
which is quite alarming.
It's about a 200% increase year on year across
Australia and the UK. We don't actually have a figure here in New Zealand because
there's not specific data available, but it seems to be that we're
following that trend.
Netsafe have reported that they receive daily calls
about deepfaking, which I think is quite alarming in itself.
There's currently limited or no support for victims, because
until somebody is effectively charged,
that doesn't kick in, which I think is a huge reason as to why we need to do
something in this space.
Under the current Harmful Digital Communications Act, there are provisions
to be able to proceed with this type of
harm through the court process. But what we've found is because
deepfaking or artificially created imagery
is actually left silent within the legislation, given the Harmful Digital
Communications Act is nearly 10 years old,
it becomes challenging and difficult to get a prosecution.
So it appears that police,
certainly in some of the cases that I'm aware of, don't tend to take this
any further. There was a case earlier this year
where
four young female victims managed to take a case,
and there was a prosecution under Harmful Digital Communications Act.
The issue is, is because it's not explicitly a crime in the Crimes Act, you have
to prove that harm and that intention to harm, and it becomes really tricky.
And in fact, it was the victim's family herself that actually gathered
all the information
to build the case, and the victims were very fortunate to have that
family
available to be able to do that.
Given that there's been a whole bunch of submissions on the bill, I think that
there is definitely some little concerns about the wording that I think the Select
Committee should look into.
Why it's important that we change both the Crimes Act and the Harmful Digital
Communications Act, I think, is the point around making it explicitly clear
to do this is in fact a crime, so you don't have to prove
that harm factor the same way that you would have to right now.
I think it's also important to note that in New Zealand we don't have a
hashing system or a national register for hashing.
And what that means is if your image, whether it's real or not
real, is shared without your consent online,
you can talk with Netsafe about getting a takedown notice.
But there is no register around having an image hashed and
put into a system to keep that image from
not appearing again and again. And other countries have actually moved to do that.
So I think while my bill doesn't do that, it's something that I think we should
look at and consider.
Lots of the submissions talked about wider changes around deepfaking.
There's a lot of concerns about fraudulent behavior and the negative
impacts of deepfaking in general.
My bill doesn't address that because it addresses just a really small
section, given that it's a member's bill,
around deepfaking into pornography.
In order to widen the scope, that would be a massive piece of work as
well beyond the piece of work that we're looking at now.
So while I think future governments will have to grapple with that and deal with
that, I don't believe that we should be expanding the scope of this bill.
So I'm going to leave it up for questions now, and if anyone's got anything they'd
like to ask.
Thank you. Rachel. Helen.
Great. So it's more about this is a great bill.
It's obviously necessary. Do you think
from what you've seen,
I think there was a discussion about this in the Labor government about
adding this to a bill. Do you think there's been a growth, and
how much of a growth has there been in this
kind of behavior?
Yeah, look, I think it's undoubtable that this kind of behavior is growing year
on year as AI advances. And AI is amazing.
There's lots of great things that we can do with AI.
There's always going to be bad actors that use technology to harm or abuse other
people. And I think as the technology's getting better and better, we're
seeing rises in this kind of crime for sure.
I think at the 2022 changes to revenge porn, it
was discussed about adding in AI. I think
actually Golriz from the Greens actually put in an amendment, which
wasn't actually
voted for in the end. But I know that it was something that quite a few
members did allude to needing something like this in the
future. So 100%, I just think our laws have not kept up with the pace in
which this is happening, and I think to be really clear, this is not just
like
... a what you'd call an old Photoshop, a head onto someone else's body.
This is actually creating imagery that is so real that the
only person that knows that this is fake, or the only people, is the person who
created it and the victim. It's so realistic.
Can I ask you, I know that a member's bill's narrow, but can I ask you about
education in this area?
Mm-hmm.
Often these young people are doing this to each other at a really
early age.
Mm-hmm.
Can you give me your views on whether we should be doing something to
expand education in this area?
Yeah, look, absolutely. I think education hasn't kept up with pace with
the online world, whether it's social media use, whether it's
deepfaking, all of these kind of things.
I think that is something that we should look into.
This bill, however, doesn't do that.
It just changes the act to make this a criminal behavior.
But I think why it's important to do that is I don't expect to see kids being
locked up in jail for deepfaking a peer, for example.
But what it will do is set the standard,
to say that this is so harmful that we consider it illegal.
And that in itself is really effective, and we know with revenge porn,
that we saw when that legislation came in, an initial spike in
some convictions, and it's dropped right off now.
Because I think young people know that if somebody shares your
nude, to share that on with someone else or to keep it and do something with it
later on is actually really harmful and really illegal.
So I think that this is, in a way, is about sending a signal as well,
not just making it there's some kind of criminal
liability there as well.
Thank you.
Maureen.
Thanks, Laura.
I'm wondering about how these images
are monitored or discovered.
Mm-hmm.
Because given the speed at which these things can be
transmitted, how do you find the creator, the
original creator of this, to hold them to task?
Yep, and that's a really good question, and there'll be times where you will not
find the original creator. There might be bad actors
overseas, for example, that would do this, and you might not be able to trace it
back. In nearly all of the cases that came to me,
they actually knew who the perpetrator was, because often when the image
is being used to target you like that, they want to have that kind of
embarrassment,
and they want that kind of overall harm to occur.
And they want you to know that they're doing this to you, which is actually quite
sadistic in that sense. So there is an
element of we will sometimes know who the perpetrator is, and there will be other
times that 100% we can't find out or trace who that is
because it might be they're using VPNs, they might be coming from different
jurisdictions, for example. In that case, though, I think
having a national register for hashing, in the future,
whether something we look at amending into this bill or something that a next
government looks at,
would mean at least those images or that footage, it now
has the ability to be found and taken down so quickly.
Because at the moment, a victim themselves has to actually
pay a license to have this done with another private company.
Unless, of course, it's child abuse material, which we do have that provision there
for.
I have a sup on that too, because as you've alluded to, some
of this can be foreign-
Mm-hmm
... as well. So are you aware of any
willingness to cooperate internationally with some of our more traditional
partners in this cyberspace?
Yeah, look, I think that that work is starting now, given how prolific
this is.
I think that we can probably build on the networks that we already have, and it'd
be really interesting to hear from DIA about what kind of work that they do.
It's probably a key question that the committee could put towards them, to see if
they are doing any work in the deepfake space and working
internationally. What we have seen overseas is that there have been things like
websites established. There was something called Mr. Deepfakes.
Was a UK-based website where people were uploading deepfake
nudes
of people, usually exes and things like that.
And that ended up being tracked back to a pharmacist
in Singapore, who was actually held accountable that way because they worked
internationally to collaborate on it.
So look, I think it is happening, but I think it'd be really interesting to
know how New Zealand can be part of that.
And it's the same with that national register of hashing.
There is a way that we might be able to information share with that as well to try
and be able to cover a lot more ground in this area.
But it's moving, it's really quickly moving.
And I don't think any government's ever going to be fast enough to do enough,
but I think that doesn't mean we don't do anything.
Marie Manal.
Thank you, Laura.
Firstly, mihi atoanukea koe, bringing this through, Laura.
Thank you.
I'm interested in the harm piece, I guess,
and whether you've noticed or heard or know of anything
that's showing up for the harm young people
suicide contemplation.
Mm-hmm.
Do you know whether these are things-- Do you know as that
showed up anywhere in the research?
Look, I know of two cases. One
suicide in New Zealand. It wasn't just deepfaking, but definitely there was a
deepfaking element to it, and there was also one attempted suicide
by
a young girl, as young as she was only 13, so year nine.
So those are just the two that I've been made aware of, because whanau have
reached out. But look, I think because the type of graphic
images that young, particularly young girls, but I have had a couple of
young guys now as well, it is changing,
have found themselves in, it's usually
really horrible and things that they would never ever do.
And it's just really disgusting, and I
know sharing actual nudes that you have sent to someone in the past is horrible as
well. There is an element of
you know that these images could be out there.
With this, it's like you have absolutely no idea until somebody sends you a link.
And often people think they're real, and so that harm
just continues-
Which can be real challenging. And at the moment, I know there's a couple of
victims where their images are just still popping up continually, like time and
time again.
Yeah.
Just well done on bringing this bill, and broad support across
Parliament for it.
I guess maybe my question goes to the
acceleration of technology, which you touched on in your opening comments.
But I'm interested in what advice you got on why the Harmful Digital Communications
Act, which was enacted in 2015-
Mm
... wasn't sufficient to address this particular issue, which
sort of AI is now enabling.
Yeah, look, I think 10 years, the landscape of AI has just changed
completely. Even in the last two years, the use of AI and
its ability to be able to do the things we actually want it to do is becoming more
and more credible, and it's easier to use.
There's a lot of open source information out there and free technology.
So I think, with all best intentions, when the Harmful Digital
Communications Act was established in 2015,
I think that it wasn't foreseeing
the age in which we would be living in now or the realities of what we're
living in now. And I think,
not to dismantle the HDCA, but there's a lot of areas where it's no longer, I
think, fit for purpose and probably needs a full review.
And that's on notice to the next parliament. Or the next minister in charge.
Yeah.
Can I ask one, Richard?
Sure.
Just about that, we've obviously had...
There's a lot of actors out there who've created these platforms, and it is
possible to stop this happening at source,
isn't it? We
found it with Elon Musk's one, where he actually had
to pull back on the capacity. This is stuff that
just is totally unacceptable, isn't it?
Yeah.
But we need to actually look at those sources.
Yeah, look, that's-
And say it's not okay to create this capacity.
Look, that is absolutely something that I think should be considered, not
necessarily with this bill, but in wider work around
the internet space. A couple of things, though.
When I deepfaked myself, I didn't need to go far to find it.
There was thousands of websites that you could do this on.
Yeah. Mm.
To try and put some kind of ban on this type of website and technology
would be a bit like playing whack-a-mole.
Doesn't mean you don't do it, but it could be really challenging.
The site that I ended up using didn't even mention nudity.
So to be able to
put some sort of blanket ban on a product or AI in order to stop
them having this function available would be really challenging.
In saying that, countries that have made it explicitly illegal to do
this,
there has been a change in, say, like the Apple Play Store
or the Samsung Play Store around apps that actually have this
ability being uploaded because they say, "Oh, it's illegal in this
jurisdiction to deepfake somebody into nude." So that you're seeing less and less
of them popping up. The same with, that Grok is a really good example.
Straightaway they said, "If it's illegal in a country, our product would've not
offered that." So while they shouldn't be offering that anyway,
that is definitely an argument. I think this is a first step in
starting that process, is saying that it's actually illegal to do this.
And then, yeah, you can look at the software, the technology later on.
But that is actually going to be really hard with AI, and how you do that in the
future, and how we manage it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Two more questions. Maureen?
Just a very quick one, Laura.
So the bill talks about the creation of
the images.
Mm-hmm.
Is transmission of those images also part of what
you're trying to capture?
Yes, it should be. As it amends part of the Harmful Digital Communications Act to
do with revenge porn, that sharing aspect should be included, but I
think it's a really good question to check with advisors if it is.
But yeah, that would be the intention there, to include the sharing, because the
sharing is actually where the real harm actually occurs.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah. And the creating of it, you may not even know if someone's created it
of you, but the sharing is where you actually find
out if it's happened or not.
Yeah.
Last question. Martha.
Yeah, I wanted to ask about,
we were just touching on it in terms of the platforms themselves.
Mm-hmm.
And
the safeguards and regulations around what the platforms
deliver into New Zealand, and then what we can do to hold them
to account for having these enabling technologies.
Your bill doesn't address that, but-
Yeah
... have you explored any of that?
Yeah, look, I haven't with this particular bill, but it's definitely forefront of
mind around what
are we going to do in the future. And I think a lot of this has been discussed with
the under-16 social media ban.
Is there going to be some sort of regulation of technology?
I think, globally, we are seeing changes in this space.
I think there's risks and there's opportunities there.
And so my answer would probably be quite political.
Yeah.
But I do think that there is going to need to be some kind of ethics with
AI.
And the AI, the technology that you're creating, if it can do these things on its
own free will, you can also pop parameters in there to stop it doing that.
So I think
that is probably a bigger picture, and it's something that I think MB
potentially should be looking at around AI and its regulation as well.
Not necessarily just platforms, but the whole landscape of AI.
Mm.
Well, thank you very much, Laura. Appreciate you coming in and talking to us.
Thank you. Yeah.
See you shortly.